# 大家好 今天天氣比較好哦 剛好把刀磿一下
Hi everyone! The weather today is rather good. Just now I’m sharpening this knife.
# 你看這個刀都已經生鏽了 我去上山砍點柴
Look! This knife is already rusted. I’m going onto the hill and chop some firewood.
# 砍點柴用來 用來煮一下那個豬食
I’m gonna pick some firewood, and cook some, some pigwash.
# 這幾天的豬都餓的不行啦
The pigs are starving to death these days.
# 砍點柴回來煮熟 把那個豬食煮熟 煮熟來再給它吃
I’l gonna chop some firewood and then cook it, I mean, cook the pigwash. Then I can feed them.
# 好啦 這個磿利啦
Alright! It’s sharp enough now.
# 去山上
Onto the hill!
# 山上砍點下來
Onto the hill and chop some back here.
# 搞個樹枝給它吃
Let me get them some branches.
# 這羊很喜歡吃這個樹葉的哦
The goats really like these leaves, you know.
# 你看 這羊肉包 天天跟豬混在一起哦
Look! This Lamb Bun, he’s mingling with the pigs every day.
# 不來的 它不跟 那大羊一起去玩
He’s not coming. He doesn’t, doesn’t play with the big goats.
# 你看這兩隻稍微大了一點 它們去洗澡了哦
Look! These two have grown up a bit. They have taken a bath.
# 天氣太熱了
It’s too hot now.
# 這裡有條捷徑哦
Here’s a shortcut.
# 每天山羊都從這裡 從這裡飛檐走壁
The goats go up along this path every day, flying through the cliffs and slopes.
# 其實我也可以
In fact, I can do the same as well.
# 你看 好久都沒來這裡砍竹子啦
Look! I haven’t been chopping bamboos here for a long time.
# 路都看不到啦
I can hardly see the path now.
# 清一下 清一下這個路
Let me clear, clear the path.
# 這些都可以用來當柴火啦
These can all be used as firewood.
# 把這個擺整齊 整整齊齊
They need to be put tidily, neatly and tidily.
# 這樣梱起來 這樣就紥實了這樣
Tie them up. So they’re firmly tied now.
# 要 綁著它要綁兩頭哦 如果綁一頭的話 很容易散掉啦
I gotta, I gotta tie on both ends. It might easily get loosened if it’s only tied on one end.
# 你看 這裡有一個杉樹哦 這杉樹已經死了
Look! Here’s a cypress. But this cypress is already dead.
# 所以把它砍下來
So I’ve chopped it down.
# 本來這個杉樹能值幾塊錢的 死了就不值錢了
In fact, this cypress should be worth a few bucks. But now it’s dead. It isn't worth anything.
# 這個杉樹表面很多刺的哦
The surface of this cypress is very spiky, you know.
# 但是經過我這樣
But after my, you know,
# 幫它條一下 修的
my polishing. It’s now,
# 光滑光滑的
shiny and smooth.
# 把這個要削尖一點哦 不削灰一點插不進去的
It needs to be sharpened a bit. Otherwise I can't pierce it in.
# 要削的 鋒利無比
It needs to be, as sharp as knife.
# 把這 插進去
Then, I can pierce it in.
# 你看 就這樣直接抬回去啦
Look! Then I can carry it back right away.
# 你看 這個黃蜂 差點就把那個蜜蜂蟄走啦
Look! This wasp, my bee was almost taken away by this wasp.
# 我就拍扁了它 你看 屁股一截都被我 攔腰折斷
So I smashed it. Look! I smashed a part of its butt, from its waist.
# 這個可以用來泡酒的哦
This can be used to make infused liquor. you know.
# 泡的酒適合我們這樣的三十歲以上的人吃
The infused liquor is really nice for those in their thirties, like us.
# 很補的
It’s really good for health.
# 你看 又打了一個 這個就是它的鍋就掛樹上的 這種蜂
Look! Here’s another one. This one have the hives hanging on the tree, this kind of wasps.
# 剛才我打的那個就是地 地下的
The previous one lived on the ground, underground.
# 它住地下
They live underground.
# 很危險的呦 這蟄要打針的哦
They’re really dangerous, you know. Antivenom is needed if you got stung.
# 好像又打了一個
It seems that I’ve killed another one.
# 兩個 這裡兩個
These two, these two here
# 你看 這些馬蜂太壞啦
Look! These wasps are really bad guys.
# 天天捉那個蜜子的哦 一下來就蟄
They catch the, the honey bees, you know. They catch every time they come down.
# 咬一個蜂 咬一個那個
Once they bite the bee, bite the, I mean,
# 那個小蜜蜂 它就把它就 就飛跑啦
the little bees, they, they fly away immediately.
# 它以吃蜜蜂為主
They mainly feed on bees.
# 太壞了這些蜂 來一個我殺一個
These wasps are simply too bad. No wasp can leave here alive.
# 這三個是那個 住地下的 地雷蜂 我們這邊叫地雷蜂
These three are, you know, living underground. Landmine wasps. Here we call them landmine wasps.
# 這個就是住樹上的 我們叫小馬蜂 這個沒那麼大
These are living in the tree. We call them little wasps. These are not that big.
# 它們都以吃這個 吃肉為主的這種
They mainly feed on, you know, mainly feed on meat, these wasps.
# 你看這個蜜蜂 就是被這個大黃蜂
Look! The bee, was caught by the,
# 吊著 吊起來被我拍下來的
caught by the wasp. I slapped it down.
# 被它蟄了一下
It was stung.
# 就被這個大黃蜂蟄一下 這個蜂蜜就
Just a single sting by this wasp, and this bee is,
# 一命鳴呼啦
is already dying.
# 大個七八倍哦 這個
It’s seven or eight times larger, the wasp.
# 你看 太壞拉它們
Look! They’re simply too bad.
# 都是還活的
They’re still alive.
# 還沒完全死亡 但是它的針已經沒啦 被我削掉啦
They’re not completely dead. But the sting is no longer there. I’ve chopped it away.
# 這樣才安全一點 要不然蟄下真的要打針的 這個
It’s much safer. Otherwise, antivenom is a must if anyone gets stung, really.
# 不打針的話這全身都會痛
Othwerise, the pain may spread throughout the body.
# 來一個我就殺一個 來一百個我就殺一百個
No wasp can leave here alive, be it one wasp or a hundred wasps.
# 來一窩 把你的窩都掏掉
If I see a hive, I’m gonna raid the hive.
# 拿來泡酒
Then take everything to make infused liquor.
# 這些就不要啦 下次 下次巿空我去把它的窩挖回來
But not this time. Next time, next time when I have more time, I’m gonna raid their hive and take it back.
# 那麼大 真的 人都被它蟄死 這種 這種馬蜂
It’s so big, really. It kills, if something is stung by this, this kind of wasps.
# 你看 它屁股裡面全是空的哦
Look! Its butt is all empty inside, you know,
# 就一根腸子在那裡 甚麼都沒有那根腸子應該是
except a single gut inside. Nothing else. I think they gut should be,
# 輸 輸毒液的
trans, transfusing the venom.
# 針都被我拍下來啦
I’ve already slapped off the sting.
# 叫你不老實 吃了我多少小蜜蜂
It’s all because you’re bad. How many bees have you eaten from my place?
# 你看 這個是毒針哦 那麼長
Look! This is the venomous sting. It’s so long.
# 插入人體的話 有致拿的風險哦
There's a lethal risk if it's pierced into human body.
# 這個針很鋒利的 你看
This sting is really sharp. Look!
# 戳進去都沒反應去
The leaf is not moving at all.
# 隨便一戳就進去啦
It goes inside immediately, without much effort.
# 太壞人啦
It’s too scary.
# 皮膚的話一戳就進去了
It happens to skin as well. It goes inside immediately.
# 像這種杆都可以戳的進
It can pierce this kind of stem as well.
# 你看戳這個杆
Have a look at this stem.
# 好殘忍啊 你看 戳進去了
So cruel! Look! It’s inside now.
# 插在這裡 誒呀 太危險了
It’s pierced into the stem. Eya! Too dangerous.
# 我還是 放在火堆裡燒掉它去算啦
I’d better, burn everything in a fire.
# 戳到人就不好啦
It would be too bad if somebody got stung.
# 你看 剛好攝影小哥家的那個紅薯 它的葉子好多的哦
Look! I just so happens that we pass by Mr. Cameraman’s sweet potatoes. There are a lot of leaves, you know.
# 搞點給豬吃
Let me fetch some for the pigs.
# 你看 他家的紅薯
Look! These are his sweet potatoes.
# 土都被撐開啦
The soil is already cracked open.
# 絕對好吃
It’s absolutely tasty.
# 連鍋端起
I’m gonna dig out everything.
# 你看 直接這個 直接可以用來餵豬的
Look! This can, this can be used to feed the pigs right away.
# 這個要把它搞的整整齊齊
I gotta place them neatly and tidily.
# 搞整齊來一點
Let me tidy them up.
# 這樣的土質種出來的紅薯才好吃
This is exactly the soil for growing tasty sweet potatoes.
# 這個就靚了哦
This is really beautiful.
# 你看 就搞了點紅薯 這個紅 紅薯藤也帶回去
Look! So we have a little bit sweet potatoes here. I’m gonna take these sweet pota, sweet potato leaves back as well.
# 你看 好薯葉也搞回來了
Look! The sweet potatoes leaves are taken back now.
# 我要把它全部切 打碎 打碎之後再用那個鍋來煮
I’m gonna cut, smash, smash them all. And then cook everything in that pot.
# 煮完之後就可以給豬吃啦
Then I can give it to the pigs.
# 你看 這個柴很瘦的哦
Look! This piece of wood is very dry and thin, you know.
# 引火很好的 以前我們家裡都用這個來引火
It glows very well. We used it to set a fire at home in the past.
# 一燒就冒煙
The smoke comes immediately.
# 你看
Look!
# 就那麼一點點
Just a tiny little bit here.
# 夠了
It’s enough.
# 你看 搞點米
Look! Put some rice.
# 加點這個 把這個葉子 把它全部搞下去
Put some, well, these leaves, put them all inside.
# 放點鹽
Put some salt.
# 這個鹽是
The salt is,
# 用來促進消化
is to enhance digestion,
# 捉進它的新陳代謝
enhance their metabolism.
# 嗯 可以
Um! Alright!
# 好啦 先慢慢燜一下
Good! Stew it for a while first.
# 蓋一下 湊個數就好了 又不是我吃
Cover it up. Quantity rather than quality. It’s not for me anyway.
# 這個就讓它慢慢煮哦 要煮半個小時左右才可以的哦
Just leave it here. It may need some time. It needs to be cooked for around half an hour, you know.
# 我洗兩個番薯吃一下
Let me wash a couple of sweet potatoes for myself first,
# 就剛挖回來的番薯
the freshly dug sweet potatoes.
# 你看 紅的
Look! It's red.
# 這個紅薯很好吃的哦 這個紅薯
These sweet potatoes are really tasty, these sweet potatoes.
# 沒有施肥料 甚麼都沒施
They’ve never been fertilised, nor taken care off.
# 就讓它自然生長 長出來的
They were simply left to grow, grow naturally.
# 賣相不好看
They don’t look really good.
# 但吃就好吃
But they taste really good.
# 我吐在這裡等下羊會下來吃掉的 那羊 甚麼都吃
I spit it here, and the goats will eat it in a while. The goats, eat everything.
# 你看 小時候我們就是這樣
Look! That’s what we did when we were small.
# 煮一大鍋 比這個鍋大十幾倍哦
We cooked with a huge pot, a dozen times larger than this one.
# 然後那個豬就吃一個 一個星期啦
And then it was enough for the pigs for a, for a whole week.
# 一個星期都不用去那個 不用去砍竹子
And we didn't need to, I mean, chop the bamboos for the whole week.
# 還沒煮爛 要等一下再爛 爛了之後才可以哦
It’s still not yet mushy. It needs a bit more time. It needs to be mushy first.
# 這個香番薯葉很貴的哦
These sweet potato leaves are really expensive, you know.
# 城市裡面都賣幾塊錢一斤
In the city, half a kilogram of them already costs a few RMB.
# 我們家裡只能餵 用來餵豬
But in the village, they’re nothing but pigwash.
# 好多 一田都是 現在都沒人要
There are a lot, all over the field. But now, nobody wants them.
# 他們砍了直接放到旁邊讓它 腐蝕掉
After chopping off the leaves, they simply throw them onto the roadside right away, and let the leaves decay.
# 再煮一下
Cook it for a bit longer.
# 不夠爛
It’s still not mushy enough.
# 你看 這個是 這是我家裡的那個米糖哦
Look! This is, this is our own rice bran.
# 在家裡面 我都是自 自己碾米吃
Here in the village, I always mill, mill my own rice.
# 碾的特別香 就 就剩下的這個米糠
It smells exceptionally good! Now only, only the rice bran is left.
# 放點下去給它
Put some into the pigwash.
# 拗一下就可以了
Stir it and it’s done.
# 現在就很香啦
Now it smells really good.
# 以前的豬食就是這樣子的
That’s how we made pigwash in the past.
# 把它抬下去 放到水裡面泡一下 太燙啦這樣
Let’s carry it there and soak it into the water. It’s too hot now.
# 等下不知道等到明天都可能餵不了
Otherwise, I don’t even know if I can feed them tomorrow.
# 讓它降下溫
Let it cool down.
# 哇 好香啊
Wa! It smells so good!
# 好香 要不要來一點
Really good! Do you want some?
# 很好吃的 不騙你的
It tastes really good! I’m not kidding.
# 很香的哦 這個哦 就是很乾淨的 就是薯藤葉加米糠
It smells so good! You know, this is really clean and pure, only sweet potato leaves and rice bran, nothing else.
# 煮出來的 就煮成這樣子
And that’s, that’s how the product looks like.
# 等冷了之後再來餵
I’ll feed it to the pigs once it cools down.
# 現在還好燙啊 冒煙
It’s still very hot. The steam is still coming out.
# 哎呦 還那麼燙
Aya! It’s still so hot.
# 等下 等下再來餵 那豬都睡覺了
Later, I’ll feed them later. The pigs are all sleeping now.
# 這個洗車的是攝影小哥買回來的 也可以當槍使
Mr. Cameraman bought it for washing the cars. But it can also be used as a gun.
# 瞄準 射擊 很準的哦
Aim! Shoot! It aims really well, you know.
# 你看 這裡有個柚子皮
Look! Here’s a pomelo peel.
# 那個豬食太難冷啦
The pigwash takes too much time to cool down.
# 把它沖一下 把它用這個匴子來裝 晾的更快一點
Let me rinse it, put the pigwash into this basin. It cools a bit faster.
# 不然等下天黑了豬都沒有晚餐吃
Otherwise the pigs couldn’t have their dinner even when it gets dark.
# 把它倒到這裡來
Let me pour everything here.
# 拿點來餵魚也可以的 這魚也喜歡吃的
It can also be used to feed the fish. The fish like it very much too.
# 這裡面養了好多魚的這裡
Here are a lot of fish, here.
# 原來是少有一百多條
There should be at least a hundred originally.
# 草魚 全是小的 很小的草魚
Grass carps, all are small, really small grass carps,
# 就手指那麼大的草魚
grass carps which are as big as a finger.
# 海浪就是這樣形成的 你看 波濤洶湧
That’s how waves are formed. Look! Roaring waves.
# 快點冷啊 我豬都等下及啦
Hurry up! My pigs are losing their patience.
# 不面的魚 感覺像地震了一樣
The fish underneath, might be experiencing an earthquake.
# 哎呀 靯都濕掉啦
Aya! My shoes get wet.
# 來給它們吃啦 那麼多
Alright! Let’s feed them. Here’s so much.
# 來啊 吃大餐啦
C’mon! Time for a big feast!
# 羊也吃 羊也吃
The goats are eating too.
Yea, the goats are eating too.
# 分開一點 這樣它們不會搶
Let me split it up, so that they won’t fight for it.
# 這裡有 這裡有哈 快吃
Here, some more here. C'mon!
# 老是打架
They’re always fighting.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我們也要吃飯啦 看它們吃的那麼香
We’re gonna have dinner too, seeing them eating so merrily.
# 這隻小公豬
This little boar…